<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Search><pages Count="12"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[3


















                                                 Rani Thippavazzula]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[5 5           The Paper Crane
                             The Paper Crane








                                                                                               Theme: Community


               Time to start




             Let us learn to make a paper dog.                                                       art integration

































































          40]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Let’s read a story and find out how a good deed helps a humble man.

          A man once owned a restaurant on a busy road. He loved to cook good food and

          he loved to serve it. He worked from morning until night and he was happy.

          But a new highway was built close by. Travellers drove straight from one place
          to another and no longer stopped at the restaurant. Many days went by when no

          guests came at all. The man became poor and had nothing to do but dust and
          polish his empty plates and tables.

          One evening a stranger came into the restaurant.

          His clothes were old and worn, but he had an                       Why do you think the       Just a Minute!
          unusual, gentle manner. Though he said he had                      restaurant owner offered food

          no money for food, the owner invited him to sit                    to the stranger without any cost?
          down. He cooked the best meal he could make                                          life skill  logical thinking
          and served him like a king. When the stranger

          had finished, he said to his host, ‘I cannot pay you with money, but I would like
          to thank you in my own way.’

          He picked up a paper napkin from the table and folded it into the shape of a

          crane. ‘You have only to clap your hands,’ he said ‘and this bird will come to life
          and dance for you. Take it, and enjoy it while it is with you.’


          With this, the stranger left.

          It happened just like the
          stranger said. The owner

          had only to clap his hands
          and the paper crane became

          a living bird, flew to the
          floor and danced. Soon
          word of the dancing crane

          spread, and people came
          from far and near to see

          the magic bird perform.


           polish: to make something smooth
           and shiny by rubbing it
           worn: damaged from long use
           unusual: different from others
           host: the person offering food
           perform: (here) to dance

                                                                                                                41]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[The owner was happy again, for

          his restaurant was always full of
          guests. He cooked and served
          and had company from morning

          until night.

          The weeks passed…and the
          months. One evening a man came

          into the restaurant. His clothes
          were old and worn, but he had an

          unusual and gentle manner. The
          owner knew him at once and was overjoyed. The stranger, however, said nothing.
          He took a flute from his pocket, raised it to his lips, and began to play.


          The crane flew down from its place on the shelf and danced as it had never
          danced before. The stranger finished playing, lowered the flute from his lips, and
                                                                        returned it to his pocket. He

                                                                        climbed on the back of the
                                                                        crane, and they flew out of the

                                                                        door and away.

                                                                        The restaurant still stands by
                                                                        the side of the road, and guests

                                                                        still come to eat the good food
                                                                        and hear the story of the gentle

                                                                        stranger and the magic crane
                                                                        made from a paper napkin. But
                                                                        neither the stranger nor the

                                                                        dancing crane has ever been
                                                                        seen again.



           overjoyed: very happy                                                                    —Molly Bang




                About the Author
                Molly Garrett Bang (b 1943) is an award-winning children’s book illustrator and author. Her works include Ten, Nine, Eight,
                The Grey Lady and the Strawberry Snatcher and When Sophie Gets Angry—Really, Really Angry.
                ‘The Paper Crane’ won the Boston Globe/Horn Book Award in 1987.





          42]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Time to answer

          A.  Select the correct option to answer the questions.


               1.  What tells you that the owner of the restaurant was hard-working?

                          The restaurant was on a busy road.

                          He loved to cook good food.

                          He worked from morning until night.


                          He dusted and polished his empty plates and dishes.


               2.  Why did the owner of the restaurant become poor?

                          because his food was not good


                          because a new highway was built and people did not stop at the restaurant

                          because he fed poor people who had no money

                          because he did not take money from strangers


               3.  Who came to the restaurant one evening?


                          a friend                                           a little girl

                          a stranger                                         an old customer


               4.  What did the old man make with the paper napkin?


                          a boat                                             a crane

                          a dog                                              a flower


               5.  Why was the owner of the restaurant happy again?

                          because his restaurant was full of guests again


                          because the paper crane danced when he clapped

                          because he had a paper crane that came to life

                          because he loved making food for strangers







                                                                                                                43]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[B.   Answer these questions.


               1.  Describe the stranger who came to the restaurant one evening.

               2.  How did the stranger thank the owner?

               3.  How did the crane help the owner of the restaurant?

               4.  What happened to the stranger and the crane in the end?


          Reference to the context

          Read the line from the story and answer the questions that follow.


           ‘Take it, and enjoy it while it is with you.’

          a.  What is ‘it’ in this sentence?

                i.   a magical crane                         ii.   a magical crow

              iii.   a magical swan                         iv.   a magical sparrow

          b.   How was ‘it’ going to help the person being spoken to?

                i.   by cooking the food                     ii.   by attracting more customers

              iii.   by cleaning the dishes                 iv.   by giving eggs

          c.   How was the person being spoken to supposed to enjoy ‘it’?

                i.   by watching its flight                  ii.   by watching its beauty

              iii.   by watching its dance                  iv.   by listening to its song


          d.   Who is the speaker?
                i.   an old customer                         ii.   a little girl


              iii.   a stranger                             iv.   a friend




                                             Time to think and answer

          1.  The owner treated the stranger well although he was poor. What does this tell us

               about the owner?                                                                       value  kindness

          2.  Do you think the stranger repaid the kindness shown by the owner of the restaurant
               well? Do you think the owner deserved it? Give reasons for your answer.

                                                                                                 life skill  critical thinking





          44]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Time to study language

          Let us learn about the different kinds of sentences.


                            Statement                                               Question

           •  Sentences that make a statement                      •  Sentences that ask a question are
               are called statements.                                   called questions.


           •  They end with a full stop (.).                       •  They end with a question mark (?).


           For example,                                            For example,
           •  A man once owned a restaurant on                     •  How can I repay you?

               a busy road.


                          Exclamation                                              Command

           •  Sentences that show surprise or                      •  Sentences that give a command are
               wonder are called exclamations.                          called commands.


           •  They end with an exclamation                         •  They end with a full stop (.).
               mark (!).
                                                                   For example,

           For example,                                            •  Take it and enjoy it.

           •  The food was delicious!                              •  Close the door when you leave.

           •  The show was amazing!


                                                         Request

           •  Sentences that make a request are called requests.

           •  A request could end with a question mark or a full stop.


           For example,

           •  Will you please help me in carrying these dishes?

           •  Bring the bill, please.



          Identify and write the kinds of sentences.

          1.   Pass me the apple, please.


          2.   Will you come to the market with me?

                                                                                                                45]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[3.   This show is fabulous!

          4.   Find out the recipe of the pumpkin pie.

          5.   Would you like to have another piece of brownie?

          6.   I am so scared!

          7.   Do not enter this room without my permission.


          8.   Risha will not come to school today.



                                              Time to learn new words


          We can add un to some words to make opposites of those words. For example,

          •  usual—unusual                    •  kind—unkind                    •  clear—unclear

          We can add over to some words to show there is too much of something. For example,

          •  overjoyed                        •  overeat


          A.  Now, add un or over to the words in the brackets and complete

               the sentences.

               1.  I                            (slept) in the morning and missed my bus.


               2.  The train was so                               (crowded) that I could not board it.

               3.  I am                              (able) to understand why she behaved so.


               4.  The actor is                              (popular) because he is never punctual.

               5.  Do not                               (load) the truck. Some things might get damaged.


               6.  My teammates are                                  (happy) because we lost the match.


          B.   Use the following words and write sentences in your own words.


               1.  unhappy

               2.  overcome


               3.  uncover

               4.  oversmart


               5.  unfold

          46]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Study skills

          We use a dictionary to find out:

          •  the meanings of words

          •  the spelling of a word

          •  how to say the words


          •  the function of a word

          Look at this page from a dictionary.
                                                                                                synthesising information























































          Now, find the meaning of these words in a dictionary.


          1. highway            2. restaurant               3. stranger           4. flute

                                                                                                                47]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Time to listen

          Listen to a few instructions and follow them to make your own paper boat.*

                                                                                                        art integration


                                                      Time to speak

          When someone helps us, we thank them. We can express our gratitude by using
          these phrases.



                                                          Thank you for
                How kind you                            taking the trouble
                are to help me.                             to help me.




                                                                                     I am very grateful
                          Thank you for                                                 that you are
                                                         That’s very                   considering my
                          spending time
                                                        kind of you.                       problem.
                              with me.




                                                                                     Thanks for
               Thank you very                                                         your kind
                     much.
                                                                                        words.


          Now, practise with your partner, what you would say in these situations.
                                                                                        st
                                                                                      21 c  communications and social skills
          •  Your friend has helped you with your homework
          •  Your teacher has appreciated your effort and praised you in class


          •  Your sister helped you make your science project

          •  A stranger in the street helped you with your baggage

          •  Someone helped you carry a big box


          •  Your friend shared his lunch with you

          •  Your mother cooked your favourite dish

          •  Your classmate helped you in mathematics homework

          •  Your parents gifted you a bicycle as a birthday present


          *  For listening text, turn to page 119.
          48]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Time to write

          Suppose you are the restaurant owner. Write a letter to the stranger thanking

          him for his kind gesture.



             Your address














             Date




             Dear





             Hope you are fine







             I am really happy








                                    thank you                                                                 .







                                                                                                               .





             Your loving friend








                                                                                                                49]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Fun time

          Let us learn how to draw a crane with the number 2.                                           art integration


           1.                                               2.






















           3.                                               4.




















































          50]]></page></pages></Search>
